<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-07-01T13:26:49+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Haris Themistocleous</title><subtitle>Charalambos K. Themistocleous</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Research Software/Packages</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2024/06/16/research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research Software/Packages" /><published>2024-06-16T10:08:40+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-16T10:08:40+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/project/2024/06/16/research</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2024/06/16/research.html"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s a selection of Python packages and utility software I’ve found valuable. This is by no means an exhaustive list, but I hope you discover something useful. Let me know if you’d like me to add any specific tools. The selection is updated regularly.</p>

<h1 id="language-analysis">Language Analysis</h1>
<h2 id="open-brain-ai">Open Brain AI</h2>
<p>Open Brain AI (OBAI) is a computational platform. First, it aims to provide advanced AI tools to facilitate spoken and written language analysis, automate the analysis process, and reduce the workload associated with time-consuming tasks.</p>

<p>The platform currently incorporates multilingual tools for English, Danish, Dutch, Finnish, French, German, Greek, Italian, Norwegian, Polish, Portuguese, Romanian, Russian, Spanish, and Swedish.</p>

<p>The tools involve models for</p>

<ul>
  <li>i. audio transcription,</li>
  <li>ii. automatic translation,</li>
  <li>iii. grammar error correction,</li>
  <li>iv. transcription to the International Phonetic Alphabet,</li>
  <li>v. readability scoring,</li>
  <li>vi phonology, morphology, syntax, semantic measures (e.g., counts and proportions), and lexical measures.</li>
</ul>

<p>Second, it aims to support clinicians in conducting their research and automating everyday tasks with “OBAI Companion,” an AI language assistant that facilitates language processing, such as structuring, summarizing, and editing texts. OBAI also provides tools for automating spelling and phonology scoring.</p>

<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="http://openbrainai.com">Open Brain AI</a></p>

<h1 id="research-studies---brain">Research Studies - Brain</h1>
<h2 id="nimare">NiMARE</h2>
<p>NiMARE is a Python package for performing meta-analyses, and derivative analyses using meta-analytic data, of the neuroimaging literature. While meta-analytic packages exist which implement one or two algorithms each, NiMARE provides a standard syntax for performing a wide range of analyses and for interacting with databases of coordinates and images from fMRI studies (e.g., brainspell, Neurosynth, and NeuroVault).</p>

<p>NiMARE joins a growing Python ecosystem for neuroimaging research, which includes such tools as Nipype, Nibabel, and Nilearn. As with these other tools, NiMARE is open source, collaboratively developed, and built with ease of use in mind.</p>

<p>This page outlines NiMARE’s purpose and its role in a proposed meta-analytic ecosystem</p>

<h2 id="conn-toolbox">Conn Toolbox</h2>
<p>CONN is a Matlab-based cross-platform software for the computation, display, and analysis of
functional connectivity in fMRI (fcMRI). Version 22 brings a number of updates and additions to previous releases. Some of the main new procedures and tools include new interactive analyses exploring the entire
brain-wide functional connectome, with a focus on descriptions of commonalities as well as heterogeneity of
functional connectivity patterns across subjects and experimental conditions (similar to AFNI instacorr but
across all subjects in a study; available in 2nd-level fc-MVPA summary tab), new preprocessing options for
normalizing anatomical and functional volumes in the presence of anatomical lesions (available in
Setup.Preprocessing), new displays for ROI-to-ROI connectivity and contingency table data (in ROI-to-ROI
results explorer), as well as the ability to create automated text, distributed under a public domain dedication
license, describing in detail the specific preprocessing, denoising, 1st- and 2nd- level analyses steps performed
on each individual CONN project (available in Tools.WriteMethods).</p>

<h2 id="neurovault">Neurovault</h2>
<p><a href="https://neurovault.org/">Neurovault</a> is an online platform that hosts
unthresholded statistical maps, including group statistical maps.
NiMARE can read these statistical maps when given a list of collection_ids.</p>

<p><strong>Website</strong>: <a href="https://neurovault.org/">Neurovault</a></p>

<h2 id="neuroquery">Neuroquery</h2>
<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://neuroquery.org">Neuroquery</a></p>

<h2 id="neurosynth-compose">Neurosynth Compose</h2>
<p><em>Neurosynth Compose</em> is the next-generation of Neurosynth, enabling users to easily perform custom neuroimaging meta-analyses using a fully web-based platform, with no programming experience required.</p>

<p><em>Neurosynth Compose</em> is <em>free to use</em> and helps users:</p>

<ul>
  <li>🔎 <strong>Search</strong> across over 20,000 studies in the Neurosynth database, or import from external databases such as PubMed.</li>
  <li>🗃️ <strong>Curate</strong> your StudySet using systematic review tools conforming to the <a href="https://www.prisma-statement.org/">PRISMA</a> guidelines.</li>
  <li>📝 <strong>Extract</strong> coordinates and metadata for each study, leveraging thousands of pre-extracted studies to minimize effort.</li>
  <li>📊 <strong>Analyze</strong> by specifying a reproducible <a href="https://readthedocs.org/projects/nimare/">NiMARE</a> workflow, and execute it locally or in the cloud.</li>
  <li>🔗 <strong>Share</strong> with the community with complete provenance and reproducibility.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Website</strong> <a href="https://compose.neurosynth.org/">Neurosynth Compose</a></p>

<h2 id="openneuro">OpenNeuro</h2>
<p>A free and open platform for validating and sharing BIDS-compliant MRI, PET, MEG, EEG, and iEEG data.</p>

<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://openneuro.org">OpenNeuro</a></p>

<h2 id="cognitive-atlas">Cognitive Atlas</h2>

<p>The Cognitive Atlas is a collaborative knowledge building project that aims to develop a knowledge base (or ontology) that characterizes the state of current thought in cognitive science. The project is led by Russell Poldrack, Professor of Psychology at Stanford University. Development of the project was supported by grant RO1MH082795 from the National Institute of Mental Health.</p>

<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="http://www.cognitiveatlas.org">Cognitive Atlas</a></p>

<h1 id="literature-and-bibliography">Literature and Bibliography</h1>
<h2 id="lisc---literature-scanner">LISC - Literature Scanner</h2>
<p>LISC acts as a wrapper and connector between available APIs, allowing users to collect data from and about scientific articles, and perform analyses on this data, such as performing automated meta-analyses.</p>

<h2 id="confidence-scanner">Confidence Scanner</h2>
<p>The Confidence Scanner is a project for automated collection and analysis of scientific text samples. The functionality can be broken into two primary steps. In the data collection phase, paper abstracts are gathered from PubMed, a repository for scientific papers specifically in Medicine and the Life Sciences, and press releases are scraped from EurekAlert, a public database for scientific press releases from a variety of research institutions and fields. Analysis consists of four different tests–Readability, Sentiment, Subjectivity, and Confidence. A paper written for the CogSci 2018 conference further detailing the analysis can be found here and a conference poster can be found here.</p>

<h1 id="biology-analysis-software">Biology Analysis Software</h1>
<h2 id="biopython">Biopython</h2>
<p>Biopython is a set of freely available tools for biological computation written in Python by an international team of developers.</p>

<p>It is a distributed collaborative effort to develop Python libraries and applications which address the needs of current and future work in bioinformatics. The source code is made available under the Biopython License, which is extremely liberal and compatible with almost every license in the world.</p>

<p>We are a member project of the Open Bioinformatics Foundation (OBF), who take care of our domain name and hosting for our mailing list etc. The OBF used to host our development repository, issue tracker and website but these are now on GitHub.</p>

<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://biopython.org">BioPython</a></p>

<h1 id="acoustic-analysis-software">Acoustic Analysis Software</h1>
<p>Praat is a computer program with which you can analyse, synthesize, and manipulate speech, and create high-quality pictures for your articles and thesis.</p>

<p><strong>Website:</strong> <a href="https://www.fon.hum.uva.nl/praat/manual/Intro.html">Praat</a></p>

<p><strong>Praat Scripts:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/themistocleous/praat_scripts">Praat Scripts</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here’s a selection of Python packages and utility software I’ve found valuable. This is by no means an exhaustive list, but I hope you discover something useful. Let me know if you’d like me to add any specific tools. The selection is updated regularly.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">OBAI Companion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2022/10/11/OBAICompanion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OBAI Companion" /><published>2022-10-11T14:08:38+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-11T14:08:38+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/project/2022/10/11/OBAICompanion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2022/10/11/OBAICompanion.html"><![CDATA[<article>
<h4>Open Brain AI (OBAI) Companion</h4>

<p>OBAI Companion is an advanced AI language model based on the Google Gemini (Generative Pre-trained Transformer) architecture. It is designed to understand and generate human-like text, facilitating a wide range of natural language processing tasks, enhancing productivity and streamlining tasks. </p>
<p>Here is an overview of what OBAI Companion is and its capabilities in writing text.</p>

<p><strong>What is OBAI Companion?</strong></p>
<ul>    
<li> <i>AI Language Model.</i> OBAI Companion is trained on a vast corpus of text data, enabling it to understand context, generate text, and engage in dialogue that mimics human conversation.</li>
<li><i>Interactivity.</i> It can engage in conversations, answer questions, provide explanations, and even emulate certain writing styles or tones.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Capabilities in Writing Text</strong></p>
<ul>
    <li><i>Content Creation.</i> OBAI Companion can assist in writing articles, essays, stories, scripts, and more, offering suggestions or generating content based on user prompts.</li>
<li><i>Editing and Proofreading.</i> It can help edit and proofread text, offering grammar corrections, style suggestions, and clarity improvements.</li>
<li><i>Language Translation.</i> While not its primary function, OBAI Companion can assist with translating text between various languages, although it might not always match the accuracy of dedicated translation models.</li>
<li> <i>Code Writing.</i> OBAI Companion, especially in versions like Codex, can assist in writing and debugging code, supporting a variety of programming languages.</li>
<li> <i>Educational Assistance.</i> It can provide explanations on a wide range of topics, assist with homework, and offer tutorials or step-by-step guides on complex subjects.</li>
<li> 	<i>Creative Writing.</i> OBAI Companion can help generate creative content, including poetry, stories, dialogue, and more, often incorporating user inputs to guide the creative direction.</li>
<li> 	<i>Business Communication.</i> It can assist in drafting business documents, emails, reports, and presentations, tailoring the content to suit professional standards and objectives.</li></ul>
    <p><strong>Interaction and Limitations</strong></p>
    <ul>
<li>	<i>User Interaction.</i> Users interact with OBAI Companion through a conversational interface, providing prompts or questions to which the model responds.</li>
<li>	<i>Limitations.</i> While OBAI Companion is powerful, it has limitations, such as the potential for inaccuracies, a lack of understanding of personal experiences or context not included in its training data, and a dependency on the quality and scope of the data it was trained on.</li>
    </ul>

<p>In essence, OBAI Companion serves as a versatile tool for a variety of text generation and processing tasks, aiding users in creating, refining, and understanding text across numerous domains and applications.</p>

</article>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Open Brain AI (OBAI) Companion]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">OBAI Editor</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2022/10/11/editor.html-20-11-37-920.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OBAI Editor" /><published>2022-10-11T14:08:38+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-11T14:08:38+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/project/2022/10/11/editor.html%2020-11-37-920</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2022/10/11/editor.html-20-11-37-920.html"><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1>Open Brain AI (OBAI) Editor Capabilities</h1>
    <h2>Getting Started</h2>
    <ul>

        <li><strong>Create an account.</strong> To create an account, follow the prompts to sign up.</li>
        <li><strong>Choose your languages.</strong> Select the source language (the language you want to work with).</li>
    </ul>
    <h2>Basic Text Formatting</h2>
    <ul>
        <li><strong>Font Styles</strong>. Apply various font styles like bold, italic, underline, and strike-through.</li>
        <li><strong>Font Size</strong>. Adjust the font size for better readability and hierarchy.</li>
        <li><strong>Text Color and Background</strong>. Change the text color and background for emphasis and appeal.</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Advanced Formatting</h2>
    <ul>
        <li><strong>Headers</strong>. Use different header levels for effective content structure.</li>
        <li><strong>Lists</strong>. Organize information with ordered and unordered lists.</li>
        <li><strong>Text Alignment</strong>. Align text to the left, right, center, or justify.</li>
        <li><strong>Links</strong>. Add hyperlinks to text for external references.</li>
    </ul>


    <h2>Code and Syntax</h2>
    <ul>
        <li><strong>Code Blocks</strong>. Insert code blocks with syntax highlighting.</li>
        <li><strong>Inline Code</strong>. Add inline code snippets within the text.</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Rich Content and Embeds</h2>
    <ul>
        <li><strong>Formula</strong>. Insert mathematical formulas using KaTeX.</li>
        <li><strong>Custom Embeds</strong>. Extend functionality with custom embeds like polls or surveys.</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Document Elements</h2>
    <ul>
        <li><strong>Blockquotes</strong>. Add blockquotes for citations or emphasis.</li>
        <li><strong>Dividers</strong>. Use horizontal lines to separate content sections.</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Collaboration and Review</h2>
    <ul>
        <li><strong>Comments</strong>. Enable commenting for collaborative feedback.</li>
        <li><strong>Track Changes</strong>. Track changes to see edits and revisions.</li>
    </ul>


    <h2>User Interface</h2>
    <ul>
        <li><strong>Toolbar</strong>. Access formatting tools through a customizable toolbar.</li>
        <li><strong>Themes</strong>. Select or customize themes to change the editor's appearance.</li>
    </ul>

</article>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Open Brain AI (OBAI) Editor Capabilities Getting Started]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Primary Progressive Aphasia?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ppa/2022/03/31/PPA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Primary Progressive Aphasia?" /><published>2022-03-31T21:12:11+02:00</published><updated>2022-03-31T21:12:11+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ppa/2022/03/31/PPA</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ppa/2022/03/31/PPA.html"><![CDATA[<p>Primary Progressive Aphasia is neurodegenerative condition. Patients are characterized by impaired speech and language production.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PPA" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Primary Progressive Aphasia is neurodegenerative condition. Patients are characterized by impaired speech and language production.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dementia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2021/12/08/blog_dementia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dementia" /><published>2021-12-08T13:08:38+01:00</published><updated>2021-12-08T13:08:38+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/project/2021/12/08/blog_dementia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2021/12/08/blog_dementia.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Sickness is an impediment that affects the body not what you choose to do (…) choose to follow this for all the things that happen to you: because you will realize that it impedes something else and not yourself.
<em>Epictetus</em>
<!--more--></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Every year more than ten million individuals develop dementia, with almost fifty-five million worldwide now living with dementia.
Dementia is the progressive deterioration of cognitive, linguistic, and social functioning that affects the quality of life, including the physical, social, and economic conditions of individuals, their families, and society.
There are types of dementia depending on the symptoms, underlying pathology.</p>

<ul>
  <li>ALZHEIMER’S DISEASE</li>
  <li>VASCULAR DEMENTIA</li>
  <li>PARKINSON’S DISEASE</li>
  <li>FRONTOTEMPORAL DEMENTIA</li>
  <li>MIXED DEMENTIA</li>
  <li>LANGUAGE SYMPTOMS</li>
</ul>

<p>Language symptoms depend on the type of dementia.</p>

<p>Individuals with Alzheimer’s Disease (AD) constitute the larger group of individuals with dementia. They are characterized by a progressive deterioration of memory, language, conversation, and ability to perform everyday activities.</p>

<p>Individuals with Primary Progressive Aphasia (PPA), a progressive neurological condition, are impaired in speech and language.</p>

<p>Individuals with PPA are grouped into three variants based on their distinct underlying neuropathology and area of brain damage.</p>

<p>According to current classification criteria, their characteristic neuropathology and damage patterns give rise to different discourse deficits across three variants, namely in</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>INDIVIDUALS WITH THE NON-FLUENT PPA VARIANT (NFVPPA)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>INDIVIDUALS WITH THE SEMANTIC PPA VARIANT (SVPPA), AND</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>INDIVIDUALS WITH THE LOGOPENIC PPA VARIANT (LVPPA)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Individuals with Parkinson’s Disease (PD) are characterized by a progressive deterioration of movement functioning, which impairs balance, speaking, language, chewing, and swallowing.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>It impairs speech, language, and communication:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Language comprehension</li>
  <li>Language production of spoken and written language</li>
  <li>Using language effectively for communication.</li>
  <li>It involves deficits in one or more language modalities, including phonetics, phonology, morphology, syntax, semantics, and pragmatics.</li>
  <li>It can also impair aspects of functional communication, e.g.,</li>
  <li>Emotions self-monitoring</li>
  <li>Theory of Mind</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="dementia-diagnosis">DEMENTIA DIAGNOSIS</h1>
<p>The neurocognitive assessment aims to evaluate individuals’ condition and provide early diagnosis, prognosis, and quantify intervention efficacy.
Computational Language Assessment (CLA) informs the clinician and the patient by quantifying the symptoms of dementia on language and enabling monitoring of disease progression over time.
CLA provides tools that can screen individuals for dementia and provide a recommendation on whether to visit a clinician.
Although there is no treatment for dementia, pharmaceutical solutions that can potentially that slow down the progression of the disease show positive results and are getting approved.
Therefore, early-stage identification, and assessment of individuals with dementia are of utmost importance to enable interventions that can delay the progression of dementia and support family planning.</p>

<h1 id="more-information">MORE INFORMATION</h1>
<ul>
  <li>American Speech-Language-Hearing Association (ASHA): <a href="http://www.asha.org">www.asha.org</a></li>
  <li>National Aphasia Association: <a href="http://www.aphasia.org/">www.aphasia.org/</a></li>
  <li>Alzheimer’s Association: <a href="https://www.alz.org">https://www.alz.org</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sickness is an impediment that affects the body not what you choose to do (…) choose to follow this for all the things that happen to you: because you will realize that it impedes something else and not yourself. Epictetus]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stuttering</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/04/blog_stuttering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stuttering" /><published>2020-11-04T09:08:40+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T09:08:40+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/04/blog_stuttering</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/04/blog_stuttering.html"><![CDATA[<p>Stuttering is a speech disorder characterized by interruptions or disfluencies in verbal expression, where individuals that stutter involuntarily repeat or prolong sounds, syllables, or words. While technically considered a symptom rather than a disease, the term “stuttering” is often used to denote both the symptom and the disorder.</p>

<p>Stuttering typically manifests during childhood, often between the ages of two and five. Many children go through a phase of “developmental stuttering” which is a normal part of language development and usually resolves on its own. However, for some children, stuttering persists and can become a chronic issue.</p>

<p>These disruptions are not easily controlled and can be both audible and silent. Stuttering often comes with additional physical movements and negative emotional responses such as fear, embarrassment, or irritation. Specifically, children who stutter may experience long- and short-term consequences:</p>

<p><strong>Communication Difficulties:</strong>  The primary consequence of stuttering is difficulty in fluent communication. This can impact a child’s ability to express their thoughts, needs, and feelings clearly.</p>

<p><strong>Emotional and Psychological Impact:</strong>  Children who stutter may become frustrated or embarrassed about their speech. This can lead to  anxiety or decreased self-esteem, especially in social or academic situations. They may also become more reserved, choosing to refrain from speaking in certain situations to avoid stuttering.</p>

<p><strong>Social Challenges:</strong>  Stuttering can affect a child’s social interactions. They may be misunderstood, teased, or bullied, resulting in social isolation.</p>

<p><strong>Educational Impact:</strong>  Stuttering can influence academic performance. Children may avoid participating in classroom discussions, reading aloud, or giving presentations, which could affect their learning and grades.</p>

<p><strong>Impact on Future Life:</strong> If left unmanaged, stuttering can persist into adulthood, affecting academic, personal, and professional life. The earlier the intervention, the better the outcomes are likely to be.&lt;/p&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Stuttering is a speech disorder characterized by interruptions or disfluencies in verbal expression, where individuals that stutter involuntarily repeat or prolong sounds, syllables, or words. While technically considered a symptom rather than a disease, the term “stuttering” is often used to denote both the symptom and the disorder.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Computational Language Assessment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/04/blog_CLA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computational Language Assessment" /><published>2020-11-04T09:08:40+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T09:08:40+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/04/blog_CLA</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/04/blog_CLA.html"><![CDATA[<article>
<p>Speech, language, and communication deficits are a common symptom in several neurodegenerative conditions. These deficits are often among the first symptoms to emerge, which makes them particularly important for early detection, diagnosis, and treatment planning. Traditional neurological assessments routinely include an evaluation of these functions as they provide critical insights into the progression of neurocognitive diseases. However, traditional speech and language evaluations pose significant challenges for clinicians as they are time-consuming and require substantial resources. In this context, we argue that the use of machine learning methodologies, natural language processing (NLP), and modern artificial intelligence (AI) for Language Assessment represents a significant improvement over conventional manual assessment methods. Open Brain AI aims to help clinicians and researchers employ CLA in their everyday practices.</p>

<p>Computational Language Assessment (CLA) leverages these advanced technologies to accomplish three primary goals. First, it enables a comprehensive neuro-cognitive evaluation of speech, language, and communication in elderly and high-risk individuals for dementia. This is crucial as early detection of dementia and other neurocognitive diseases is essential for timely intervention and better patient outcomes. Second, CLA facilitates the diagnosis, prognosis, and assessment of therapy efficacy in at-risk and language-impaired populations. This helps in personalizing treatment plans and monitoring progress over time. Third, it allows easier extensibility to assess patients from a wide range of languages. This is particularly important in a globalized world where patients may speak a variety of languages that are not always comprehensively covered by traditional assessment tools.</p>

<p>By employing advanced AI models, CLA can also provide valuable insights into the neurocognitive theory on the relationship between language symptoms and their neural bases. This can help in understanding the underlying mechanisms of language and communication deficits in neurodegenerative diseases and inform the development of more effective interventions.</p>

<p>Finally, CLA significantly advances our ability to optimize the prevention and treatment of elderly individuals with communication disorders. This is of utmost importance as communication is a key aspect of social engagement, which in turn is associated with better cognitive and emotional well-being. By improving the assessment and management of communication disorders, CLA can help elderly individuals maintain better social engagement, thereby contributing to healthier aging.</p>
</article>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Speech, language, and communication deficits are a common symptom in several neurodegenerative conditions. These deficits are often among the first symptoms to emerge, which makes them particularly important for early detection, diagnosis, and treatment planning. Traditional neurological assessments routinely include an evaluation of these functions as they provide critical insights into the progression of neurocognitive diseases. However, traditional speech and language evaluations pose significant challenges for clinicians as they are time-consuming and require substantial resources. In this context, we argue that the use of machine learning methodologies, natural language processing (NLP), and modern artificial intelligence (AI) for Language Assessment represents a significant improvement over conventional manual assessment methods. Open Brain AI aims to help clinicians and researchers employ CLA in their everyday practices.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aphasia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/03/blog_aphasia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aphasia" /><published>2020-11-03T08:11:40+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-03T08:11:40+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/03/blog_aphasia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/project/2020/11/03/blog_aphasia.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Sickness is an impediment that affects the body not what you choose to do (…) choose to follow this for all the things that happen to you: because you will realize that it impedes something else and not yourself.
<em>Epictetus</em></p>
</blockquote>

<!--more-->
<p>Aphasia is a language disorder affecting a person’s ability to communicate. It is caused by damage to the brain’s language centers, typically resulting from a stroke, brain injury, or neurodegenerative conditions.</p>

<p>ASHA defines aphasia as an acquired neurogenic communication disorder that impairs the comprehension and production of spoken and written language and the ability to use language effectively for communication. It involves deficits in one or more language modalities, including phonetics, phonology, morphology, syntax, semantics, and pragmatics.</p>

<p>Aphasia can manifest in several ways depending on the specific areas of the brain affected and the severity of the impairment. It can impact both expressive language skills (such as speaking and writing) and receptive language skills (such as understanding spoken and written language). The specific symptoms and severity of aphasia can vary widely among individuals.</p>

<p>Treatment for aphasia typically involves a comprehensive approach that includes language therapy, communication strategies, and augmentative and alternative communication (AAC) techniques. The goal is to improve communication abilities, enhance quality of life, and help individuals with aphasia participate more fully in social, academic, and vocational activities.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research" /><category term="Project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sickness is an impediment that affects the body not what you choose to do (…) choose to follow this for all the things that happen to you: because you will realize that it impedes something else and not yourself. Epictetus]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assessment</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/01/assessment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assessment" /><published>2018-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/01/assessment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/01/assessment.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Audiotranscription</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/15/audiotranscription.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Audiotranscription" /><published>2018-08-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-08-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/15/audiotranscription</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/08/15/audiotranscription.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>